A Guide to the Ruth Hanners Chambers Research Files, 1918-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Ruth Hanners Chambers, Research Files, 1918-2002
Library of Virginia
42230
1.5 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Broudy, Hampton, Virginia, 5 October 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hilton Village, the first government-built housing development in the United States, was born out of a need for worker housing in the shipbuilding industry. During World War I, a severe lack of housing prevented companies such as the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company from filling the demand for American ships from European allies. Armed with a thorough economic study of the total cost, Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company president, Homer L. Ferguson, went before the Emergency Fleet Corporation of the United States Shipping Board with a proposition. If the government would finance houses for shipyard workers, the shipyard would purchase the land, supervise the building, and rent or sell the houses to the workers under the terms agreed upon by the government. The government agreed to finance the $1.2 million project.
Influenced by the English garden cities movement, the development featured modest but well-built homes in the cottage style. Landscape architect Henry Vincent Hubbard and architect Francis Y. Joannes were responsible for the layout and design. Following the war, in 1921, the Shipping Board offered the village for sale at public auction. Henry E. Huntington, chairman of the shipyard, purchased Hilton Village and held it under the auspices of the Newport News Land Company. By 1922, the shipyard began to sell the homes to individuals. Due to the armistice, the full elaboration of the Hilton Village plan was never realized.
Scope and Content
This accession consists of articles, clippings, notes, correspondence, theses, publications, maps, photographs, and ephemera concerning the planned community of Hilton Village near Newport News, Virginia. Two women are primarily responsible for gathering the materials contained in this accession. Ruth Hanners Chambers compiled approximately half of the files during the writing of her book "Hilton Village: The Nation's First Government-built Planned Community, 1918-1968." Before her death in 1988, Chambers passed the files on to Elizabeth Broudy, who continued to research the history of the development.
The information in the files includes not only research regarding Hilton Village but other World War I-era housing projects undertaken by the United States government.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Articles, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Articles, 1919-1976, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Atlantic Heights: A World War I Shipbuilder's Community" by Richard M. Candee, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Brief History of Hilton Village" by Elizabeth Broudy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings, 1952-2002, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence- Incoming, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence- Incoming, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence- Incoming, 1968-1986, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence- Outgoing, 1961-1982, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "'An Environment Worthy of Our Civilization' Hilton Village, Virginia and The Government's Model Towns Experiments of the First World War" by Kathryn Ann Geddings, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hilton Village 60th Anniversary Program, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Hilton Village Civic and Garden Club Roster, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Hilton Village Commercial Area Master Plan, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National Register Inventory-Nomination Form, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Hilton Village Revitalization Program, Harvard Graduate School of Design, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Maps, 1918, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- National Archives and Records Administration Reproductions, 1918, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Notes, ca. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)